Guide to the Gilmore David Clarke Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Gilmore David Clarke Papers
ca.1920-1980.
Clarke, Gilmore D., 1892-1982
7.5 linear ft (ca.2,000 items in 5 boxes & 1 folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0233
4079663
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, documents, subject files, photographs, memorabilia, and printed materials of landscape architect Gilmore D. Clarke, 1892-1982.
Biographical Note
Gilmore David Clarke, American landscape architect & chairman of the National Commission of Fine Arts, died 1982.
Scope and Content
Correspondence relating to the activities of the National Commission of Fine Arts and subject files relating to his work on the New York World's Fair in 1964-1965 and to his views on the works of other architects and artists. There are also many photographs, primarily of sculptures commissioned for the World's Fair and of views of New York State parkways and gardens designed by his firm, Clarke & Rapuano. The printed materials include bound volumes of city planning studies supervised by Clarke. Major correspondents include Robert Moses, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Franklin Roosevelt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series:
Series I: Gilmore David Clarke Papers, ca.1920-1980
Subjects
United States.--Commission of Fine Arts.; National Commission on Fine Arts.; New York World's Fair (1964-1965); Adams, Sherman, 1899-1986.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Bishop, Morris, 1893-1973.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Brownell, Herbert, 1904-; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965.; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Eisenhower, Milton Stover, 1899-1985.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hersey, John, 1914-1993.; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1865-1940.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Manship, Paul, 1885-1966.; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994.; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963.; Tate, Allen, 1899-1979.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Architectural design--United States.; City planning--New York (State); Express highways.; Landscape architects.; Recreation areas.; Biographies.; Landscape architecture drawings.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 2-5. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1960 M-1960 CLARKE, GILMORE D. GIFT
Gift of Gilmore D. Clarke, 1960 (transferred from the Oral History Related Papers, 1985); bequest of Gilmore D. Clarke, 1985.
- Series I: Gilmore David Clarke Papers, ca.1920-1980
  - Cataloged correspondence
    - Adams, Sherman (Box 1)
    - Barzun, Jacques (Box 1)
    - Benton, William (Box 1)
    - Bishop, Morris (Box 1)
    - Brooks, Van Wyck (Box 1)
    - Brownell, Herbert (Box 1)
    - Churchill, Winston S. (Box 1)
    - Cowley, Malcolm (Box 1)
    - Damrosch, Walter see Brooks, Van Wyck (Box 1)
    - Day, Edmund Ezra (Box 1)
    - Delano, Frederick A. (Box 1)
    - Ecker, Frederick H. (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Milton S. (Box 1)
    - Farrand, Livingston (Box 1)
    - Herter, Christian A. (Box 1)
    - Hoover, Herbert (Box 1)
    - Hersey, John (Box 1)
    - McClellan, George B. (Box 1)
    - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 1)
    - Manship, Paul (Box 1)
    - Morris, Newbold (Box 1)
    - Moses, Robert (Box 1)
    - Mumford, Lewis (Box 1)
    - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 1)
    - Oakes, John B. (Box 1)
    - Proffitt, Charles G. (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller, John D., II (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller, John D., III (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 1)
    - Rusk, Dean (Box 1)
    - Seymour, Charles (Box 1)
    - Stassen, Harold E. (Box 1)
    - Stone, Harlan F. (Box 1)
    - Tate, Allen (Box 1)
    - Truman, Harry S. (Box 1)
  - Cataloged photographs:
    - New York City World's Fair Armillary Sphere (Box 1)
    - New York City World's Fair Sundial (Box 1)
  - Cataloged art work:
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 1)
  - Arranged correspondence
    - Clarke (Box 1)
    - A-G (Box 1)
    - H-M (Box 1)
    - N-Z (Box 1)
  - Subject files
    - Architects and Their Work
      - Breuer, Marcel (Box 2)
      - Brooklyn Queens Expressway (Box 2)
      - Grand Central Station (Box 2)
      - Hirschhorn (Box 2)
      - Nevelson, Louise (Box 2)
      - New York (Box 2)
      - Pei, I. M. (Box 2)
      - Washington, D.C. Area (Box 2)
    - Biographical File (Box 2)
    - Board of Design (Box 2)
    - Columbia University Oral History Project (Box 2)
    - Committee of Fine Arts
      - General (Box 2)
      - Potomac River (Box 2)
      - U.S. Capitol (Box 2)
      - White House (Box 2)
    - Cornell University (Box 2)
    - Franklin Institute (Box 2)
    - New York World's Fair, 1964-1965
      - Correspondence
        - August 1960-1961 (Box 2)
        - 1962-1965 (Box 3)
      - Designs (Box 3)
      - Manuscripts (Box 3)
      - Photographs
        - DeLue, Donald (Box 3)
        - Fredericks, Marshall (Box 3)
        - Roszak, Theodore (Box 3)
        - Sculptures, Misc. (Box 3)
        - Views (Box 3)
      - Printed materials (Box 3)
      - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts (Arranged) (Box 4)
    - Clarke
      - General (Box 4)
      - Memorials (Box 4)
      - Sonnets (Box 4)
    - By others, A-Z (Box 4)
  - Documents
    - Clarke family (Box 4)
    - Clarke, Gilmore D. (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Barrett Park, Staten Island (Box 4)
    - Central Park, Manhattan (Box 4)
    - Cleveland Museum of Art (Box 4)
    - Cross Bronx Parkway (Box 4)
    - Garden State Parkway (Box 4)
    - Grand Central Parkway (Box 4)
    - Henry Hudson Parkway (Box 4)
    - Hutchinson Parkway (Box 4)
    - Nashville Expressway System (Box 4)
    - New Jersey Turnpike (Box 4)
    - New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Palisades Parkway (Box 4)
    - Prospect Park, Brooklyn (Box 4)
    - Queens Botanical Gardens (Box 4)
    - Robert Moses State Park (Box 4)
    - Saw Mill River Parkway (Box 4)
    - State University College, Long Island (Stoney Brook) (Box 4)
    - Stuyvesant Town s Manhattan (Box 4)
    - Taconic State Parkway (Box 4)
    - Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority (Box 4)
    - Van Wyck Expressway (Box 4)
    - Washington, D.C. (Box 4)
    - Unidentified landscapes (Box 4)
    - Unidentified portraits (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Misc.) (Box 4)
  - Printed materials
    - Clarke (author), Illustrations, Articles (Box 5)
    - Pamphlets, Programs, Brochures (Box 5)
    - Reports and Studies, 1939-1956 (Box 5)
    - Reports and Studies, 1957-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1 Oversized Folder of Printed materials - Bound volumes (Box 14-P-3)